Finding Aid for Ransom Dunn papers, 1796-1900
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ransom Dunn papers 1796-1900
Dunn, Ransom, 1818-1900.
10 linear feet
851288 Aa 2
Free Will Baptist minister, professor and acting president of Hillsdale College. Correspondence and other materials concerning the Free Will Baptists, Hillsdale College and its predecessor, Michigan Central College at Spring Arbor, with mention of Dunn's anti-slavery and Republican Party activities; also Civil War letters from his sons, Francis Wayland Dunn and Newell Ransom Dunn.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of the Dunn-Slayton family (donor no. 3361 ) and came to the library in 1957.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Portions of the John Dunn, Ransom Dunn and Cyrena Dunn correspondence is available on microfilm.
Ransom Dunn was born in Bakersfield, Vermont, July 7, 1818. Around 1830, he joined the Free Will Baptist Church and soon thereafter decided to enter the ministry. He moved about frequently in this period. In 1837, he was in Ohio where he was ordained, then back east where he was minister at the Washington Street Free Baptist Church in Dover, New Hampshire, and later at the First Free Baptist Church of Great Falls, New Hampshire. He returned to Ohio for a period, then to New York where he did missionary work, then on to the First Free Baptist Church of Boston, Massachusetts.
In 1851, Dunn accepted appointment as professor of mental and moral philosophy in Michigan Central College, Spring Arbor, Jackson County. With the move of that school to Hillsdale, Dunn took on the additional role of fund raiser for the needed buildings on the new campus. In 1863 he became Burr Professorship of Christian Theology. From 1884 to 1886, Dunn also served as acting president of Hillsdale College. He died November 9, 1900.
The Ransom Dunn collection includes both his own papers and those of other family members, including his father John Dunn and Ransom Dunn's wife Cyrena Emery Dunn. The bulk of the collection consists of correspondence received by Ransom Dunn in the period of 1835 to 1900. These letters concern the Free Will Baptist Church and the growth and development of Hillsdale College and its predecessor, Michigan Central College at Spring Arbor. Some of the letters concern anti-slavery and Republican Party activities; others relate to personal and family affairs. Importantly, there are letters from his sons Francis Wayland Dunn and Newell Ransom Dunn, as students at Hillsdale and as soldiers serving in the Civil War. One of the letters in the collection is from Austin Blair (Feb. 23, 1853) discussing the legality of an injunction on Michigan Central College, Spring Arbor. Other portions of the collection include Dunn's writings on theological topics, sermons, diaries, and a few photographs.
Subjects:
Clergy--Michigan--Hillsdale.; Dunn, Ransom, 1818-1900.; Dunn family.; Free Will Baptists (1780?-1911); Hillsdale College.; Michigan Central College (Spring Arbor, Mich.); Presidents--United States--Election--1860.; Presidents--United States--Election--1884.; Republican Party (Mich.); Antislavery movements--United States.; Spring Arbor (Mich.); United States. Army. Illinois Infantry Regiment, 64th (1861-1865); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Dwellings--Michigan--Hillsdale.; Hillsdale (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Interiors--Michigan--Hillsdale.; Private libraries.
Contributors:
Blair, Austin, 1818-1894.; Dunn, Cyrena Emery, 1824-1896.; Dunn, Francis Wayland, 1843-1874.; Dunn, John.; Dunn, Newell Ransom, 1841-1863.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Stereographs.
- John Dunn
  - Correspondence, 1796-1836, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (microfilm available for 1792-1832)
- Ransom Dunn
  - Correspondence, 1835-1900
    - 1835-1854, 56 folders (Box 1)
      (microfilm available for 1835-1846)
    - 1855-1861, 41 folders (Box 2)
    - 1862-1868, 42 folders (Box 3)
    - 1869-1876, 38 folders (Box 4)
    - 1877-1884, 36 folders (Box 5)
    - 1885-August 1889, 29 folders (Box 6)
    - September 1889-1895, 33 folders (Box 7)
    - 1896-November 1900, 25 folders (Box 8)
  - Writings on Theology, 7 folders (Box 8)
  - Writings on Theology, 27 folders (Box 9)
  - Graduation oration (Box 9)
  - Moral and political papers (include temperance) (Box 9)
  - Certificates of ministry (Box 9)
  - Marriage licenses (Box 9)
  - Marriage certificates (Box 9)
  - Business miscellanea (insurance, deeds, bank records, etc.), 2 folders (Box 9)
    (includes subscription list of individuals donating to foundation of Hillsdale College, 1853-55)
  - Receipts, 9 folders (Box 9)
  - Miscellanea (include passport), 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Diaries, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Sermon notes and notebooks (Box 10)
  - Notebook of letters received on 80th birthday, 1898 (Box 10)
- Cyrena Emery Dunn
  - Correspondence, 1838-1896, 26 folders (Box 10)
    (microfilm available for 1838-1845)
- Lewis Slayton
  - Hillsdale College and course work (Box 10)
- Photographs
  - Portraits and photographs of his home and study in Hillsdale, Michigan (Box 10)
Related Material
Collections of papers of Ransom Dunn's sons, Francis Wayland Dunn and Newell Ransom Dunn have been separately cataloged. There is also a separate collection of papers for the Slayton family.